A Guide to the Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, RG 2 FA433
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Office of the Messieurs Rockefeller (OMR) Files, 1878-1972; bulk; 2; 21 Cubic Feet
  - Business Interests, 1946-1967; bulk; 3; 9 box(es)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Organization (II), [1958] (Box 23, Folder 312)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Organization (III), 1958 November-1959 (Box 23, Folder 313)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Other Hotel Openings, 1957-1958; Still Images: 3 black-and-white 8" x 10" prints. (Box 23, Folder 314)
      Includes 3 press-release photos, circa 1958, of San Juan Intercontinental hotel, San Jose public housing development, and rain forest.
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Photographs, 1958-1959; Still Image: black-and-white 5" x 7" print. (Box 23, Folder 315)
      Includes photograph of Ruth Compton and three other golfers [Bo Wininger, Ed Carter, and Bob Newlin?], enclosed in Carlisle H. Humelsine to Allston Boyer, March 18, 1959.
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Pre-Opening Inspection Groups, 1957 October-November (Box 23, Folder 316)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Speeches, 1958-1959 (Box 23, Folder 317)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Supplies, 1958-1959 (Box 24, Folder 318)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Thank-You Letters - General, 1958 December (Box 24, Folder 319)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Thank-You Letters - McCaskey, Thomas G., and Gerald Flamm, 1958 December - 1959 January (Box 24, Folder 320)
      Golf Tournament
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Thank-You Letters - Rockefeller, Laurance S. and Robert L. Hoke, 1958 December (Box 24, Folder 321)
      Opening and transportation
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Transportation, 1958 October - November (Box 24, Folder 322)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Transportation, 1958 December - 1960 (Box 24, Folder 323)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel - Opening Public Relations - Travel Agent Reception (New York), 1958 October - November (Box 24, Folder 324)
    - Estate Good Hope - General, 1959-1961 (Box 24, Folder 325)
    - Estate Good Hope - Financial Statements, 1961 (Box 24, Folder 326)
    - Hawaii, 1960-1961 (Box 24, Folder 327)
    - Howard Hughes Negotiations, 1954-1955 (Box 24, Folder 328)
    - John Paul Jones Film, 1957-1959 (Box 24, Folder 329)
    - Possible Business Interests, 1946-1947, 1954-1961; Still Image: black-and-white photograph (3.75" x 4.25"). (Box 24, Folder 330)
      Includes product photo of Klear-Glass lens cleaning station, enclosed in Percy Lawson-Johnston (Buckley Corporation) to LSR, December 17, 1954.
    - Puerto Rico, 1952-1957 (Box 24, Folder 331)
    - Puerto Rico, 1958-1961, 1963 (Box 24, Folder 332)
    - Virgin Gorda, 1959-1961 (Box 24, Folder 333)
    - Virgin Islands - General, 1952-1954; Still Image: black-and-white photograph (2.75" x 4.5"). (Box 24, Folder 334)
      Includes photo of Joan of Arc sculpture by Julius Wadsworth, enclosed in Wadsworth to LSR, February 19, 1953.
    - Virgin Islands - General, 1955 (Box 25, Folder 335)
    - Virgin Islands - General, 1956-1958 (Box 25, Folder 336)
    - Virgin Islands - General, 1959 (Box 25, Folder 337)
    - Virgin Islands - General, 1960-1961 (Box 25, Folder 338)
    - Virgin Islands - General, 1956, 1961 (Box 25, Folder 338 A)
    - Virgin Islands - Applicants for Employment, 1956-1961 (Box 25, Folder 339)
    - Virgin Islands - Bluebeard's Castle, 1953-1958 (Box 25, Folder 340)
    - Virgin Islands - St. John, 1954-1961 (Box 25, Folder 341)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1953-1954 (Box 25, Folder 342)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1955 January - June (Box 25, Folder 343)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1955 July - December (Box 25, Folder 344)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1956 January - April (Drawer E11, Drawer 56, Box 25, Folder 345)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1956 June - December (Box 25, Folder 346)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1957 January - June (Box 25, Folder 347)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1957 July - December; Still Image: black-and-white print (4" x 5"). (Box 25, Folder 348)
      Includes snapshot photo of Mrs. Frank J. Mather III and record Allison (yellow-fin) tuna.
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1958 (Box 25, Folder 349)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1959-1960 (Box 26, Folder 350)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank, 1961-1963, 1966-1967 (Box 26, Folder 351)
    - Virgin Islands - Stick, Frank (Oversized file), 1955 (Box 53, Folder 708)
      Coral Tribune (Florida Keys and Key West, Florida), 1955
    - Cornwell Productions; Dorado, Puerto Rico: Municipal Beach; Dorado Beach Hotel; Virgin Islands: St. John (Oversized file), 1954-1959 (Box 53, Folder 707)
      Includes brochure for ""Janet Dean, Registered Nurse"" series, 1954; drawings pertaining to Dorado Municipal Beach property, 1956-1959; Dorado Beach Hotel seating plan for opening dinner and Golf Club menu, 1958; sketch of Community Hall, St. John, 1956
  - Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1914-1961 (bulk 1947-1961); bulk; 4; 15 box(es)
    Some files relating to Memorial Hospital Staff and Treatment contain personnel-related or private medical information, and are restricted from scholarly access.
    Arrangement
    The arrangement of records in this series reflects the interconnections and divisions between Memorial and Sloan-Kettering Institute. Because Memorial and SKI did not merge until 1960, there are separate files for each institution, but the bulk of the records concerns Memorial Hospital. Files addressing common issues or overlapping concerns such as fundraising, general facilities, staff, operations, and organization generally fall under Memorial Hospital. Files concerning the relation with Cornell University are found under SKI and also in the Agreements files under Memorial Hospital.
    Records relating to LSR's leadership at Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center (MSKCC) form the largest series of his OMR files.
    LSR was elected to the Board of Managers of Memorial Hospital for the Treatment of Cancer and Allied Diseases on December 16, 1947, and soon served as assistant treasurer and as a member of the executive, finance, planning, real estate, and Normandy Realty committees. By early 1950, LSR chaired Memorial's executive committee and had been elected a trustee of the Sloan-Kettering Institute. LSR became president of the renamed Memorial Center for Cancer and Allied Diseases in February 1950, and he served in that position until April 1960, when he assumed the chair of the newly consolidated MSKCC.
    The Rockefeller family was an early benefactor of the Memorial Hospital (originally the New York Cancer Hospital, founded in 1884). John D. Rockefeller, Jr. purchased the property on which the hospital stands, and the General Education Board donated $3 million in 1935 for construction of the new building. JDR, Jr. had also funded James Ewing's cancer research, and he made significant pledges in 1948, 1949, and 1954 that added impetus to the administrative reforms and development programs that LSR was spearheading.
    The records in this series underscore Memorial Center's complicated organizational history. Memorial Hospital was the treatment arm of the partnership, providing hospital care and clinical treatment for cancer patients. Memorial's nurses and physicians staffed the James Ewing Hospital, established by the City of New York for the care of indigent patients. It also encompassed the Strang Cancer Prevention Center, which provided cancer screening and prevention services.
    The Sloan-Kettering Institute for Cancer Research (SKI) was established in 1945 as the research division of Memorial Hospital. While Memorial owned the property and was responsible for all fundraising, SKI increasingly asserted corporate autonomy, and the records attest to the sometimes difficult efforts to streamline and negotiate the organizational and financial relationship between the two institutions. LSR's tenure at Memorial Hospital from the late 1940s to 1960 oversaw these negotiations which culminated in the successful merger of Memorial Center and the Sloan-Kettering Institute into MSKCC in April 1960.
    Sloan-Kettering and Memorial had a third institutional connection with Cornell University Medical College and its affiliate New York Hospital. In June 1950, Sloan-Kettering and Memorial contracted with Cornell University to become part of the Medical College's program of graduate teaching. They also shared physicians and patients with New York Hospital.
    Significant topics in this series include the administrative history of the two institutions and their continual efforts to define and coordinate their relationship to each other; the expansion and modernization of the physical facilities (air conditioning, the construction and/or renovation of hospital facilities such as the Children's Pavilion or the Tower Clinic, new laboratories and new technologies, new staff housing for nurses and physicians, and related architectural and space planning studies); and to a lesser extent the local impact of the center's expansion (Normandy Realty, tenant relocation, and the York Avenue Redevelopment Plan). Equally significant are files on the fundraising efforts and endowments that undergirded the Center's expansion, research, and operations, and that sought to ensure a foundation for teaching and research going forward. Several files concern relations – cooperative and competitive – with other cancer agencies with regard to fundraising and research support and with the auxiliary Society of Memorial Cancer Center. While several files touch on hospital operations, the 1953 Organization Survey presents a detailed review of hospital administration ("organization and control") at Memorial Center.
    The general files under Memorial Hospital and Sloan-Kettering Institute as well as files on the American Cancer Society, offer glimpses into the history of cancer research and treatment. Topics include research in chemotherapy and radiation therapy, as well as considerations of the psychological impact of cancer and of links between biochemistry and mental disease. There is notably also in the Memorial and SKI general files some discussion of connections between smoking and cancer. Publicity files (for Memorial and for SKI) and files on laboratories such as the Meyer Physiology Laboratory and Betatron Unit, the Firestone Department of Radiation Therapy (endowed by the Firestone Fund) and, under SKI, the Proposed New Laboratory (East 68th St.) and the Walker Laboratory (for testing of new Chemotherapy substances), also provide some insight into research and treatment programs. The file on Francelia Butler contains a partial draft of a proposed history of cancer and Memorial Hospital.
    There is an extensive and complicated correspondence with Alfred P. Sloan, Jr., throughout the MSKCC series, but especially in files on Memorial Hospital – Agreements, Organization (Correspondence), and Housing (Sloan Contribution); and in files on Sloan-Kettering Institute – By-Laws and Incorporation, and Walker Laboratory.
    Other significant correspondents include Warren Weaver, Reginald G. Coombe, Cornelius (C. P. "Dusty") Rhoads, Henry T. Randall, Frank Drake, Frank A. Howard, Ogden White, Raymond Baarts, Richard Vanderwarker, and Robert Moses.
    - James Ewing Hospital - General, 1948-1961; Still Image: black-and-white glossy print (8" x 10"). (Box 26, Folder 352)
      Includes photo of holiday decoration in James Ewing Hospital lobby, December 1956.
    - James Ewing Hospital - Arrangement with New York City, 1950-1951 (Box 26, Folder 353)
    - James Ewing Hospital - Arrangement with New York City, 1952-1957 (Box 26, Folder 354)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1938, 1947 (Box 26, Folder 355)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1948 (Box 26, Folder 356)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 357)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1950 January-April (Box 26, Folder 358)
      Carlton report; LSR election as president; Women's Society
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1950 May-July (Box 26, Folder 359)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1950 August-December (Box 26, Folder 360)
      Children's Pavilion dedication; JDR, Jr. donation
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1951 January-August (Box 26, Folder 361)
      appropriation of New York State funds for cancer research and teaching; Memorial Center and national military scientific effort; Philadelpia cancer research; President's Quadrennial Report, 1946-1950
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1951 September-December (Box 26, Folder 362)
      Alice Hill Chittenden Memorial; Sloan Foundation funding
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1952 January-March (Box 27, Folder 363)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1952 January-March (Box 27, Folder 363 A)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1952 April-June (Box 27, Folder 364)
      Report on Solicitation of Privately Owned firms
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1952 July-September (Box 27, Folder 365)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1952 July-September (Box 27, Folder 365 A)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1952 October-December (Box 27, Folder 366)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1953 January-May (Box 27, Folder 367)
      Crosby Research Institute; Memorial Chapel; Jeanne Kerbs
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1953 June-July (Box 27, Folder 368)
      Nancy Milburn Weekes Fund; Henry T. Randall report on Medical Education
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1953 August-December (Box 27, Folder 369)
      Woodside Animal Colony; Fleischmann Foundation
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1954 January-February (Box 27, Folder 370)
      Anesthesia residency training program; Robert Taft Memorial; support activities; Bing Crosby; Assurance fund dinner; Airborne Instruments Laboratory, Inc.
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1954 March (Box 27, Folder 371)
      Educational Program report; Frank Drake fundraising trip and Howard Hughes Medical Foundation
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1954 March (Box 27, Folder 371 A)
      Restricted - Confidential information.
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1954 April-June (Box 27, Folder 372)
      Vera Goeller; Camp Uncas; Airborne Instruments laboratory
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1954 April-June (Box 27, Folder 372 A)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1954 July-December (Box 27, Folder 373)
      Atomic tests hazards; William Zeckendorf purchase of Old Memorial hospital building
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1954 July-December (Box 27, Folder 373 A)
      Restriced - Confidential material.
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1955 January-May (Box 27, Folder 374)
      Nursery School; C. P. Rhoads and Biophysical Facility; Thomas Randall
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1955 June-December (Box 27, Folder 375)
      Proposed Radiation Institute for Biophysical Research; surgery training; management engineering study; proposed fulltime presidency
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1956 (Box 28, Folder 376)
      James Foundation; clerkship program for medical students
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1957 January-August (Box 28, Folder 377)
      Sloan Awards; Frank Drake; George Escher steroid study
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1957 September-December; Still Image: sepia-tone glossy print (3.75" x 5.75"), attached to letter. (Box 28, Folder 378)
      Lloyd Craver and Medical Neoplasia Service; Hubert C. Winans cancer cure; Rulon Rawson; Van de Graaff Isotope Laboratory; Mrs. V. Beaumont Allen and nursing program. Includes image of National Rehabilitation Center building (at National Jewish Hospital, Denver), built by Vivian Beaumont Allen in memory of her father, [1957].
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1958 January-April 12 (Box 28, Folder 379)
      Accreditation reports
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1958 April 25-28 (Box 28, Folder 380)
      Arthur M. Sutherland, research on psychological impact of cancer
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1958 April 30-December (Box 28, Folder 381)
      George T. Pack; proposed study of Education Program
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1958 April 30-December (Box 28, Folder 381 A)
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1959 January-August (Box 28, Folder 382)
      Collective bargaining legislation; Warren Weaver memorandum on Memorial Center and SKI
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1959 September (Box 28, Folder 383)
      Space needs and proposed research-hospital building
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1959 October-December (Box 28, Folder 384)
      New York State Department of Social Welfare inspections
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 385)
      Gracie Square Hospital; Warren Weaver and Scientific Policy Committee; Elizabeth Hamilton Cullen portrait; new research program on external and internal factors in cancer, and support from industries and tobacco companies
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1961 January-May (Box 29, Folder 386)
      Arnold Hutschnecker and proposed research on relation between personality and cancer; unemployment insurance legislation; Eleanor Roosevelt Cancer Foundation.
    - Memorial Hospital - General, 1961 June-December (Box 29, Folder 387)
      Canadian Cancer Society; Memorial art show; Richard Vanderwarker; MSKCC organization; memorandum on management of general services
    - Memorial Hospital: General (Oversized file), 1950-1953 (Box 53, Folder 709)
    - Memorial Hospital - Agreements, 1945, 1950 (Box 29, Folder 388)
      Deed of gift and Agreement between Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, Inc. and Memorial Hospital, August 7, 1945, forming Sloan Kettering Institute
    - Memorial Hospital - Agreements, 1952 (Box 29, Folder 389)
    - Memorial Hospital - Agreements, 1953 January-May (Box 29, Folder 390)
    - Memorial Hospital - Agreements, 1953 June-1955, 1957 (Box 29, Folder 391)
      Research contingency reserve fund; relation to Cornell University Medical College
    - Memorial Hospital - Agreements, 1958 January-February (Box 29, Folder 392)
      Alfred P. Sloan, Jr., and Frank Howard Proposal for Re-Alignment of Memorial Center and SKI; nurses residence
    - Memorial Hospital - Agreements, 1958 March-May (Box 29, Folder 393)
      Alfred P. Sloan, Jr. and relation between Memorial Center and SKI
    - Memorial Hospital - Agreements, 1958 June-1959 (Box 29, Folder 394)
      Joint policy committee; nurses residence
    - Memorial Hospital - Agreements, 1960 (Box 29, Folder 395)
      MSKCC agreement, April 1, 1960
    - Memorial Hospital - American Cancer Society, 1948-1950 (Box 30, Folder 396)
      Includes New York City Cancer Committee
    - Memorial Hospital - American Cancer Society, 1951-1952 (Box 30, Folder 397)
    - Memorial Hospital - American Cancer Society, 1953-1956, 1958-1960 (Box 30, Folder 398)
    - Memorial Hospital - Bequests - General, 1914-1917, 1948, 1950-1952 (Box 30, Folder 399)
      James Douglas bequests, 1914-1917
    - Memorial Hospital - Bequests - General, 1953-1956 (Box 30, Folder 400)
    - Memorial Hospital - Bequests - General, 1957-1961 (Box 30, Folder 401)
      Donald S. Walker bequest, 1957-1958
    - Memorial Hospital - Black-Stevenson Cancer Foundation, 1951-1954 (Box 30, Folder 402)
      Bequest split between Presbyterian Hospital in Newark, New Jersey, and Memorial Hospital
    - Memorial Hospital - Butler, Francelia, 1951-1952 May (Box 30, Folder 403)
      File includes 2 chapters of manuscript, written with Dr. Hayes Martin, on history of Memorial Hospital and cancer research.
    - Memorial Hospital - Butler, Francelia, 1952 July-December (Box 30, Folder 404)
    - Memorial Hospital - Butler, Francelia, 1953-1955 (Box 30, Folder 405)
      The Sun Dial, 1952; Cancer through the Ages, 1955.
    - Memorial Hospital - By-Laws and Incorporation, 1947-1952 (Box 31, Folder 406)
    - Memorial Hospital - By-Laws and Incorporation, 1953-1957 (Box 31, Folder 407)
    - Memorial Hospital - By-Laws and Incorporation, 1958-1960 (Box 31, Folder 408)
    - Memorial Hospital - By-Laws and Incorporation, [1961] (Box 31, Folder 409)
    - Memorial Hospital - Children's Memorial Cancer Fund, 1951-1961 (Box 31, Folder 410)
      Fan Ball
    - Memorial Hospital - Children's Pavilion Opening, 1950, 1952 (Box 31, Folder 411)
    - Memorial Hospital - Civil Defense Program, 1950-1952 (Box 31, Folder 412)
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - General (A-D) (Box 31, Folder 413)
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - General (E-I) (Box 31, Folder 414)
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - General (J-M) (Box 31, Folder 415)
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - General (N-R) (Box 31, Folder 416)
      John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution of securities valued at $500,000, 1955-1956.
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - General (S-Z) (Box 31, Folder 417)
      Includes Summary of Contributions made by Alfred P. Sloan, Jr. and Sloan Foundation, 1942-1957
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - Assurance Fund, 1953 (Box 32, Folder 418)
      Campaign to raise $10 million in unrestricted gifts to assure current programs and provide reserve funds for future teaching or research needs. Announcement dinner, March 2, 1954.
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - Assurance Fund, 1954 (Box 32, Folder 419)
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - Assurance Fund, 1955-1956 (Box 32, Folder 420)
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - Assurance Fund, 1957-1958 (Box 32, Folder 421)
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - Building Fund, 1950, 1952 (Box 32, Folder 422)
      Includes 1952 memorandum on acoustics in Main Dining Room
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - Rockefeller, Laurance S., 1949-1956 (Box 32, Folder 423)
      Includes Report on Gifts to Memorial Center-SKI, 1950-1954, prepared by R. E. Baarts, January 18, 1955.
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - Rockefeller, Laurance S., 1957-1961 (Box 32, Folder 424)
    - Memorial Hospital - Contributions - Seventy-Fifth Anniversary Fund, 1960-1961 (Box 32, Folder 425)
    - Memorial Hospital - Corporate Reorganization (Memorial and Sloan-Kettering Institute), 1959 March-October (Box 32, Folder 426)
      Report by Industrial Relations Counselors on Employee Relations Problems Arising from the Relationship between Memorial and Sloan-Kettering Institute, March 16, 1959.
    - Memorial Hospital - Corporate Reorganization (Memorial and SKI), 1959 November (Box 32, Folder 427)
    - Memorial Hospital - Corporate Reorganization (Memorial and SKI), 1959 December (Box 32, Folder 428)
    - Memorial Hospital - Corporate Reorganization (Memorial and SKI), 1960 (Box 32, Folder 429)
      Plan of reorganization, March 9, 1960.
    - Memorial Hospital - Damon Runyon Memorial Fund for Cancer Research - General, 1950-1953, 1958 (Box 32, Folder 430)
      Fund established 1946 by Walter Winchell.
    - Memorial Hospital - Damon Runyon Memorial Fund for Cancer Research - Essay Contest, 1952-1953 (Box 32, Folder 431)
      Statements on "Why I should Vote" to be submitted with $1 contribution. LSR underwrites prizes.
    - Memorial Hospital - Expansion Program - General, 1948-1951 (Box 33, Folder 432)
      Housing for staff and nurses; construction program and budgets; physiology laboratory (1949); air conditioning. Includes tinted photostat of drawing, "Part 1 of Proposed Overall Planning Program showing Scope of Additional New Construction, Memorial Hospital Center," May 26, 1948 (enclosed in T. Voyvodick to LSR, August 18, 1948).
    - Memorial Hospital - Expansion Program - General, 1959-1961 (Box 33, Folder 433)